The magical moment, the magical moment of conducting.
الدقيقة السحرية... الدقيقة السحرية فى قيادة الاوركسترا
Which is, you go onto a stage. There is an orchestra sitting.
هى عندما تقف على المسرح وفريق الاوركسترا جالسون
They are all, you know, warming up and doing stuff.
وجمعيهم - كما تعلمون - يعزفون عشوائياً استعداداً للسيمفونية
And I go on the podium.
وعندما اصعد على المنصة
You know, this little office of the conductor.
تعلمون هذا المكتب الصغير الخاص بقائد الاوركسترا
Or rather a cubicle, an open-space cubicle,
او بالأصح حجرة صغيرة، حجرة صغيرة بلا حوائط
with a lot of space.
بها مساحات كبيرة
And in front of all that noise,
وأمام كل هذه الضوضاء
you do a very small gesture.
تشير مجرد إشارة بسيطة جدا
Something like this, not very pomp, not very sophisticated, this.
إشارة كهذه، ليست سريعة وغير معقدة، هكذا
And suddenly, out of the chaos, order.
وفجأة، من بعد الفوضى يأتى النظام
Noise becomes music.
الضوضاء تتحول الى موسيقى
And this is fantastic. And it's so tempting
وهذا شىء مذهل، ويغريك
to think that it's all about me.
بان تظن ان الفضل كله لك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All those great people here, virtuosos,
،جميع هؤلاء الموسيقيين العظماء الموهوبون
they make noise, they need me to do that.
يصدرون ضوضاء ويحتاجوننى لفرض النظام
Not really. If it were that,
بالطبع لا. ان كان الأمر هكذا
I would just save you the talk,
،لكنت وفرت عليكم هذا الحديث
and teach you the gesture.
وعلمتكم فقط هذه الإشارة
So you could go out to the world
ليمكنكم الذهاب الى العالم
and do this thing in whatever company or whatever you want,
والقيام بهذه الإشارة بشركتكم أو بأينما اردتم
and you have perfect harmony. It doesn't work.
ولحظيتم بالتناغم المثالى، ولكن هذا لا يفلح
Let's look at the first video.
دعنا نشاهد المشهد الأول
I hope you'll think it's a good example of harmony.
أتمنى ان تظنون انه مثال جيد للتناغم
And then speak a little bit about how it comes about.
ثم سنتكلم قليلا عمَا يدور
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Was that nice?
ألم يكن ذلك لطيفاً؟
So that was a sort of a success.
اذن هذا كان نوع من النجاح
Now, who should we thank for the success?
الآن، من يستوجب الشكر لهذا النجاح؟
I mean, obviously the orchestra musicians
أعنى، من الواضح ان عازفى الاوركسترا
playing beautifully,
يعزفون بجمال
the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra.
"أوركسترا "فيينا فيلهارمونيك
They don't often even look at the conductor.
انهم لا ينظرون الى قائد الاوركسترا كثيرا
Then you have the clapping audience, yeah,
ثم تجد ان تصفيق المستمعون
actually taking part in doing the music.
يلعب جزء فى آداء الموسيقى
You know Viennese audiences usually don't interfere with the music.
مع العلم بأن جمهور "فيينا" لا يقاطعون الموسيقى
This is the closest to an Oriental bellydancing feast
فهذا أشبه باحتفالية رقص شرقى
that you will ever get in Vienna.
"والتى نادرا ما تحدث بـ "فيينا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Unlike, for example Israel, where audiences cough all the time.
على العكس فى إسرائيل على سبيل المثال، حيث ان الجمهور يسعلون فى جميع الأوقات
You know, Arthur Rubinstein, the pianist, used to say
تعرفون "أرثر روبنستاين" عازف البيانو، اعتاد ان يقول
that, "Anywhere in the world, people that have the flu, they go to the doctor.
عادة ما يذهب المصابون بالأنفلونزا فى جميع دول العالم إلى الطبيب"
In Tel Aviv they come to my concerts."
".لكن بـ "تل أبيب" يذهبون الى حفلاتى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So that's a sort of a tradition.
هذه عادة عندهم
But Viennese audiences do not do that.
لكن جمهور "فيينا" لا يفعلون ذلك
Here they go out of their regular, just to be part of that,
هاهم يقومون بشىء مختلف، ليكون جزء من
to become part of the orchestra, and that's great.
ليكونون جزء من الأوركسترا وهذا شىء جيد
You know, audiences like you, yeah,
تعلمون، المستمعون أمثالكم
make the event.
هم من يصنعون الحدث
But what about the conductor? What can you say
لكن ماذا عن قائد الأوركسترا؟ ماذا يمكنكم أن تقولون
the conductor was doing, actually?
عمَا كان يفعله قائد الأوركسترا؟
Um, he was happy.
اممم، انه كان سعيد
And I often show this to senior management.
وعادة عندما اعرض هذا على المديرين ذوى الخبرة
People get annoyed.
فإنهم ينزعجون
"You come to work. How come you're so happy?"
"كيف يمكنك أن تسعد بمجيئك الى العمل؟"
Something must be wrong there, yeah? But he's spreading happiness.
إذن فهناك شىء خاطىء، اليس كذلك؟ ولكنه يبعث السعادة
And I think the happiness, the important thing is this happiness
وأنا أظن أن أهم ما بالسعادة
does not come from
لا يأتى
only his own story and his joy of the music.
من مجرد قصته هو، واستمتاعه بالموسيقى
The joy is about enabling other people's stories
ولكنها تأتى من تمكين قصص الآخرين
to be heard at the same time.
بأن يتم السماع اليها فى نفس الوقت
You have the story of the orchestra as a professional body.
يمكنك سماع قصة الأوركسترا ككيان مهنى
You have the story of the audience as a community. Yeah.
وسماع قصة المستمعون كمجتمع
You have the stories of the individuals
هنالك قصص أفراد
in the orchestra and in the audience.
بين فريق الأوركسترا وبين المستمعين
And then you have other stories, unseen.
وهنالك أيضاً قصص أخرى غير مرئية
People who build this wonderful concert hall.
هؤلاء من قاموا ببناء هذه القاعة الجميلة
People who made those Stradivarius, Amati, all those beautiful instruments.
قصص من صنعوا هذه الالآت الموسيقية الجميلة
And all those stories are being heard at the same time.
وجميع هذه القصص تستمع اليها فى نفس الوقت
This is the true experience of a live concert.
هذه هى التجربة الحقيقية للعروض الموسيقية المباشرة
That's a reason to go out of home. Yeah?
هذا هو سبب الخروج من المنزل، أليس كذلك؟
And not all conductors do just that.
لكن ليس كل قائدى الأوركسترا يقومون بذلك
Let's see somebody else, a great conductor.
دعونا نرى شخص آخر، قائد أوركسترا عظيم
Riccardo Muti, please.
ريكاردو موتى" من فضلك"
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Yeah, that was very short, but you could see
نعم، هذا كان قصيرا. لكن يمكنك رؤية
it's a completely different figure. Right?
انه مثال مختلف تماما. أليس كذلك؟
He's awesome. He's so commanding. Yeah?
انه رائع. انه متحكم جداً
So clear. Maybe a little bit over-clear.
واضح للغاية. ربما واضح زيادة عن اللزوم
Can we have a little demonstration? Would you be my orchestra for a second?
سأقوم بعمل مثال صغير. هل يمكنكم أن تكونوا فريقى للاوركسترا لثانية؟
Can you sing, please, the first note of Don Giovanni?
أيمكنكم غناء أول مقطوعة لـ "دون جيوفانى" من فضلكم؟
You have to sing "Aaaaaah," and I'll stop you.
ستغنون "آآآآآآه"، وسأقوم انا بإيقافكم
Okay? Ready?
حسنا؟ مستعدون؟
Audience: ♫ Aaaaaaah ... ♫
المستمعون: ♫ آآآآآآآآآآآه... ♫
Itay Talgam: Come on, with me. If you do it without me
إتاى تالجام": افعلوها معى، فإن لم تفعلوا"
I feel even more redundant than I already feel.
سأشعر بأنى غير مرغوب بى أكثر مما أشعر به بالفعل
So please, wait for the conductor.
لذا من فضلكم انتظروا قائد الاوركسترا
Now look at me. "Aaaaaah," and I stop you. Let's go.
هيا، انظروا الىّ. قولوا "آآآآآه" وسأقوم بإيقافكم. هيا بنا
Audience: ♫ ... Aaaaaaaah ... ♫
المستمعون: ♫ ... آآآآآآآآآه ...♫
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Itay Talgam: So we'll have a little chat later.
إتاى تالجام: نحتاج للتحدث لاحقاً
But ... There is a vacancy for a ...
لكن... هنالك فرصة عمل لـ...
But -- (Laughter)
لكن ...
-- you could see that you could stop an orchestra with a finger.
يمكنك رؤية بانه يمكنك إيقاف الأوركسترا بإصبع ...
Now what does Riccardo Muti do? He does something like this ...
...وما الذى يفعله "ريكاردو موتى"؟ يفعل شىء كهذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then -- sort of -- (Laughter)
ثم-- نوعاً ما --
So not only the instruction is clear,
لذا ليس فقط أن التوجيهات واضحة
but also the sanction, what will happen if you don't do what I tell you.
ولكن العقاب أيضاً واضح. ما سيحدث ان لم تفعل ما اقوله لك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, does it work? Yes, it works --
-- فهل هذا ينجح؟ نعم، انه كذلك
to a certain point.
الى حد معين
When Muti is asked, "Why do you conduct like this?"
"عندما سؤل "موتى"، "لماذا تقود هكذا؟
He says, "I'm responsible."
".عندها قال، "أنا مسئول
Responsible in front of him.
مسئول أمامه
No he doesn't really mean Him. He means Mozart,
"انه لا يعنى امام "الله". انه يعنى "موزارت
which is -- (Laughter) -- like a third seat from the center.
حيث يقبع كأنه بثالث كرسى من المنتصف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So he says, "If I'm --
--لذا هو يقول، " ان كنت
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
if I'm responsible for Mozart,
"ان كنت مسئولاً امام "موزارت
this is going to be the only story to be told.
فهذه هى القصة الوحيدة التى ستُحكى
It's Mozart as I, Riccardo Muti, understand it."
"انها كما "موزارت" وأنا "ريكاردو موتى" نفهمها
And you know what happened to Muti?
وتعرفون ما حدث لـ "موتى"؟
Three years ago he got a letter signed by
من ثلاثة سنوات استلم رسالة موقعة من
all 700 employees of La Scala,
"جميع الـ 700 موظف بمدينة "لا سكالا
musical employees, I mean the musicians,
الموظفين الموسيقيين، أعنى العازفين
saying, "You're a great conductor. We don't want to work with you. Please resign."
".تقول، "انت قائد أوركسترا عظيم. نحن لا نريد العمل معك. من فضلك استقيل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Why? Because you don't let us develop.
"لماذا؟ لأنك لا تدعنا نقوم بالتطوير
You're using us as instruments, not as partners.
انت تستخدمنا كآلآت. وليس كشركاء
And our joy of music, etc., etc. ..."
"... ومتعتنا بالموسيقى، الخ الخ
So he had to resign. Isn't that nice?
لذا اضطر الى الاستقالة. أليس ذلك لطيفاً؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He's a nice guy. He's a really nice guy.
انه رجل لطيف. لطيف جداً
Well, can you do it with less control,
حسناً. هل يمكنك التوجيه بقدر اقل من التحكم،
or with a different kind of control?
أو بشكل آخر من التحكم؟
Let's look at the next conductor, Richard Strauss.
"دعونا نشاهد قائد الأوركسترا التالى، "ريتشارد ستراوس
(Music)
(موسيقى)
I'm afraid you'll get the feeling that I really picked on him because he's old.
أخشى ان تشعرون بأننى اخترته لأنه عجوز
It's not true. When he was a young man
ليس حقيقى. عندما كان شاباً
of about 30, he wrote what he called
فى حوالى الثلاثون من عمره. قام بكتابة ما سمّاه
"The Ten Commandments for Conductors."
" الوصايا العشر لقائدى الأوركسترا"
The first one was: If you sweat by the end of the concert
الاولى كانت: ان عرقت بنهاية الحفلة
it means that you must have done something wrong.
فيعنى ذلك بأنك تفعل شىء خاطىء
That's the first one. The fourth one you'll like better.
هذه الوصية الاولى. الرابعة ستعجبكم أكثر
It says: Never look at the trombones --
"تقول: لا تنظر أبداً الى عازفى "البوق
it only encourages them.
فهذا يقوم بتشجيعهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, the whole idea is really to let
لذا، فالفكرة كلها بأن تجعلها
it happen by itself.
تحدث بنفسها
Do not interfere.
فلا تقاطع
But how does it happen? Did you see
لكن كيف يحدث ذلك؟ هل تراه
him turning pages in the score?
وهو يقلب صفحات النوتة الموسيقية؟
Now, either he is senile,
إمّا انه شاخ
and doesn't remember his own music, because he wrote the music.
ولا يمكنه تذكر موسيقاه، لانه من كتب الموسيقى
Or he is actually transferring a very strong message to them, saying,
أو انه يرسل لهم رسالة قوية تقول
"Come on guys. You have to play by the book.
يجب أن تعزفون كما قال الكتاب"
So it's not about my story. It's not about your story.
لذا انها ليست عن قصتى أو عن قصتكم
It's only the execution of the written music,
انها فقط تنفيذ للموسيقى المكتوبة
no interpretation."
".بلا أى ترجمة
Interpretation is the real story of the performer.
والترجمة هى قصة العازف الحقيقية
So, no, he doesn't want that. That's a different kind of control.
إنه لا يريد ذلك، وهذا نوع مختلف من التحكم
Let's see another super-conductor,
لنرى قائد أوركسترا خارق آخر
a German super-conductor. Herbert von Karajan, please.
قائد اوركسترا ألمانى خارق، "هيربرت فون كارايان" من فضلك
(Music)
(موسيقى)
What's different? Did you see the eyes? Closed.
ما الاختلاف؟ هل رايتم عيناه؟ مغلقة
Did you see the hands?
هل رأيتم يداه؟
Did you see this kind of movement? Let me conduct you. Twice.
هل رأيتم نوع الحركة؟ دعونى أقودكم مرتين
Once like a Muti, and you'll -- (Claps) -- clap, just once.
مرة مثل "موتى"، وستقومون بالتصفيق مرة واحدة
And then like Karajan. Let's see what happens. Okay?
ومرة مثل "كارايان" ودعونا نرى ما سيحدث. حسناً؟
Like Muti. You ready? Because Muti ...
..."مثلا "موتى". مستعدون؟ لان "موتى
(Laughter) Okay? Ready? Let's do it.
حسناً؟ مستعدون؟ هيا بنا
Audience: (Claps)
(المستمعون يصفقون)
Itay Talgam: Hmm ... again.
إتاى تالجام": هممم... مرة اخرى"
Itay Talgam: Good. Now like a Karajan. Since you're already trained,
إتاى تالجام": جيد. الآن مثل "كارايان". كما تمرنتم بالضبط
let me concentrate, close my eyes. Come, come.
دعونى أركز، أغلق عيناى. هيا، هيا
Audience: (Claps) (Laughter)
(المستمعون يصفقون ثم يضحكون)
Itay Talgam: Why not together? (Laughter)
إتاى تالجام": لما ليس سوياً؟
Because you didn't know when to play.
لانكم لا تعرفون متى تعزفون
Now I can tell you, even the Berlin Philharmonic
الآن يمكننى القول بأن حتى فريق "فيلهارمونيك" الالمانى
doesn't know when to play.
لا يعرف متى يعزف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I'll tell you how they do it. No cynicism.
لكننى سأقول لكم كيف يفعلونها. بلا سخرية
This is a German orchestra, yes?
هذه أوركسترا ألمانى. حسنا؟
They look at Karajan. And then they look at each other.
انهم ينظرون الى "كارايان". ثم ينظرون الى بعضهم البعض
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Do you understand what this guy wants?"
"هل تفهم ما يريده هذا الرجل؟"
And after doing that,
وبعدما يحدث ذلك
they really look at each other, and the first players of the orchestra
ينظرون بجدية الى بعضهم البعض، والعازفون الاوّلون بالاوركسترا
lead the whole ensemble in playing together.
يقودون الفرقة كلها ويعزفون مع بعض
And when Karajan is asked about it
وعندما سُئِل "كارايان" عن ذلك
he actually says, "Yes, the worst damage
فقال "نعم، أسوأ ضرر
I can do to my orchestra
يمكننى فعله بفريقى
is to give them a clear instruction.
بأن اعطيهم توجيهات واضحة
Because that would
لأن ذلك بإمكانه
prevent the ensemble, the listening to each other
منع الوحدة بينهم، بين الإستماع الى بعضهم البعض
that is needed for an orchestra."
".هو ما يحتاجه الأوركسترا بالفعل
Now that's great. What about the eyes?
وهذا عظيم. فماذا عن العينين؟
Why are the eyes closed?
لما هم مغلقان؟
There is a wonderful story about Karajan conducting in London.
هناك قصة رائعة عن "كارايان" فى لندن
And he cues in a flute player like this.
ويشير الى عازف "فلوت" هكذا
The guy has no idea what to do. (Laughter)
(والعازف ليس عنده فكرة عمّا يجب فعله. (ضحك
"Maestro, with all due respect, when should I start?"
"مايسترو، مع إحترامى الفائق، متى يجب البدء؟"
What do you think Karajan's reply was? When should I start?
ما بإعتقادكم كان رد "كارايان"؟ متى يجب البدء؟
Oh yeah. He says, "You start when you can't stand it anymore."
"نعم، لقد قال "تبدأ عندما لا يمكنك الاحتمال أكثر من ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Meaning that you know you have no authority to change anything.
بمعنى انك تعرف انك لا تملك الأحقية فى تغيير أى شىء
It's my music. The real music is only in Karajan's head.
"انها موسيقاى. الموسيقى الحقيقية برأس "كارايان
And you have to guess my mind. So you are under tremendous pressure
ويجب أن تخمن ما بذهنى. لذا فأنت تحت ضغط رهيب
because I don't give you instruction,
لأننى لا اعطيك التوجيهات
and yet, you have to guess my mind.
ومع ذلك، يجب أن تخمن ما بذهنى
So it's a different kind of, a very spiritual but yet
هذا نوع مختلف، روحانى للغاية ولكن مع ذلك
very firm control.
تحكمى بشكل راسخ
Can we do it in another way? Of course we can. Let's go back
أيمكننا فعلها بطريقة اخرى؟ بالطبع يمكن. دعونا نعود
to the first conductor we've seen:
إلى أول قائد اوركسترا رأيناه
Carlos Kleiber, his name. Next video, please.
اسمه "كارلوس كلايبر". المقطع التالى من فضلك
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Laughter) Yeah.
نعم
Well, it is different. But isn't that controlling in the same way?
انه مختلف. لكن أليس يقوم بالتحكم بشكل مختلف؟
No, it's not, because he is not telling them what to do.
ليس كذلك. لانه لا يخبرهم بما يجب فعله
When he does this, it's not,
عندما يفعل ذلك، فإنه لا يعنى
"Take your Stradivarius and like Jimi Hendrix,
"امسك بآلتك وكما فعل "جيمي هندريكس"
smash it on the floor." It's not that.
حطمها على الأرض" بالطبع ليست كذلك
He says, "This is the gesture of the music.
انه يقول "هذه حواس الموسيقى
I'm opening a space for you
وانا افتح مساحة لك
to put in another layer
لكى تضيف طبقة أخرى
of interpretation."
"من الترجمة الموسيقية
That is another story.
هذه قصة اخرى
But how does it really work together
لكن كيف يعملون سوياً
if it doesn't give them instructions?
ان لم يأخذوا توجيهات؟
It's like being on a rollercoaster. Yeah?
انها مثل دوامة الملاهى
You're not really given any instructions,
انت لا تستلم اية تعليمات
but the forces of the process itself keep you in place.
ولكن قوى العملية نفسها تبقيك فى الاتجاه
That's what he does.
وهو ما يفعله
The interesting thing is of course the rollercoaster does not really exist.
والشىء المثير أن دوامة الملاهى غير متواجدة بالفعل
It's not a physical thing. It's in the players' heads.
انها ليست بشىء ملموس. انها بعقول اللاعبين
And that's what makes them into partners.
وهو ما يجعلهم شركاء
You have the plan in your head.
تعرف الخطة فى رأسك
You know what to do, even though Kleiber is not conducting you.
وتعرف ما يجب فعله، بالرغم أن "كلايبر" لا يقوم بتوجيههم
But here and there and that. You know what to do.
ولكن هكذا هنا وهناك، تعرف ما يحب فعله
And you become a partner building the rollercoaster,
وتصبح شريك فى بناء دوامة الملاهى
yeah, with sound,
نعم، بالموسيقى
as you actually take the ride.
بينما تستمتع بالقيادة
This is very exciting for those players.
انه لشىء مثير جداً بالنسبة لهؤلاء الموسيقيين
They do need to go to a sanatorium for two weeks, later.
ويحتاجون للذهاب الى المصحة لمدة اسبوعين بعد ذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is very tiring. Yeah?
انه شىء متعب للغاية
But it's the best music making, like this.
ولكنه أفضل صناعة للموسيقى
But of course it's not only about motivation
ولكنه بالطبع ليس مجرد تحفيز
and giving them a lot of physical energy.
واعطائهم الكثير من الطاقة الجثمانية
You also have to be very professional.
ولكن يجب ان تكون محترف جدا
And look again at this Kleiber.
وانظروا الى هذا مجددا
Can we have the next video, quickly?
أيمكننا رؤية الفيديو التالى سريعاً؟
You'll see what happens when there is a mistake.
سترون ما يحدث عندما يحدث خطأ
(Music) Again you see the beautiful body language.
مجدداً ترون لغة الجسد الرائعة
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And now there is a trumpet player who
والآن سيقوم عازف بوق
does something not exactly the way it should be done.
بالعزف ليس كما يجب
Go along with the video. Look.
انظروا الى الفيديو
See, second time for the same player.
أترون، خطأ اخر لنفس العازف
(Laughter) And now the third time for the same player.
والآن ثالث مرة لنفس العازف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Wait for me after the concert.
انتظرنى بعد الحفلة"
I have a short notice to give you."
"عندى تحذير اليك
You know, when it's needed, the authority is there. It's very important.
عندما توجد الحاجة الى السُلطة فإنها موجودة. انها فى غاية الأهمية
But authority is not enough to make people your partners.
ولكن السُلطة لا تكفى لجعل الناس شركائك
Let's see the next video, please. See what happens here.
دعونا نرى الفيديو التالى من فضلكم لنرى ما يحدث
You might be surprised having seen Kleiber
"ربما ستُذهلون لرؤية "كلايبر
as such a hyperactive guy.
كشخص نشيط للغاية
He's conducting Mozart.
"انه يعزف مقطوعة لـ "موزارت
(Music)
(موسيقى)
The whole orchestra is playing.
كل الأوركسترا تقوم بالعزف
Now something else.
الآن شىء آخر
(Music)
(موسيقى)
See? He is there 100 percent,
ترون؟ انه حاضر مائة بالمائة
but not commanding, not telling what to do.
ولكن لا يقوم بالتحكم. لا يقول ما يجب فعله
Rather enjoying what the soloist is doing.
ولكنه يستمتع بما يقوم به العازف
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Another solo now. See what you can pick up from this.
عازف منفرد آخر. ترون ما يمكنكم استنباطه من هنا
Look at the eyes.
انظروا الى العينان
Okay. You see that?
حسنا. اترون ذلك؟
First of all, it's a kind of a compliment we all like to get.
مبدأياً، انه نوع من المجاملة كما نحب جميعاً أن نحظى
It's not feedback. It's an "Mmmm ..." Yeah, it comes from here.
انه ليس رد فعل. انه "امممم..." نعم، تخرج من هنا
So that's a good thing.
لذا هذا شىء جيد
And the second thing is
والشىء الآخر هو
it's about actually being in control,
انه كونك مسيطر
but in a very special way.
ولكن بشكل خاص جداً
When Kleiber does -- did you see the eyes,
عندما فعلها "كلايبر"-- هل رأيتم العينان
going from here? (Singing)
تذهبان هكذا؟
You know what happens? Gravitation is no more.
تعرفون ما يحدث؟ لم يعد هناك جاذبية
Kleiber not only creates a process,
لا يقوم "كلايبر" بمجرد خلق السياق نفسه
but also creates the conditions in the world
ولكنه يخلق ايضاً القواعد بالعالم
in which this process takes place.
حيثما تحدث هذه العملية
So again, the oboe player
وهكذا عازف المزمار
is completely autonomous
يعزف بإستقلالية
and therefore happy and proud of his work,
وهو سعيد وفخور بعمله
and creative and all of that.
ويقوم بالابتكار وما الى ذلك
And the level in which Kleiber is in control is in a different level.
والمرحلة التى يقوم "كلايبر" بالتحكم منها هى مرحلة مختلفة
So control is no longer a zero-sum game.
لذا فالتحكم لا يؤدى الى مكسب احد وخسارة احد آخر
You have this control. You have this control. And all you put together,
بتحكمك بهذا وذاك. ووضعهم معاً
in partnership, brings about the best music.
بشكل تشاركى. تنبثق افضل الموسيقى
So Kleiber is about process.
لذا فـأسلوب "كلايبر" يتلخص فى السياق بذاته
Kleiber is about conditions in the world.
ويتلخص فى القواعد بالعالم
But you need to have process and content to create the meaning.
ولكن يحتاج الى السياق والمحتوى لخلق معنى
Lenny Bernstein, my own personal maestro.
لينى بيرنستاين"، المايسترو الخاص بى"
Since he was a great teacher,
ولأنه كان مدرس عظيم
Lenny Bernstein always started from the meaning. Look at this, please.
يبدأ "لينى بيرنستاين" دائماً بالمعنى. انظروا الى هذا من فضلكم
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Do you remember the face of Muti, at the beginning?
أتذكرون وجه "موتى" بالبداية؟
Well he had a wonderful expression, but only one.
انه كان يحتفظ بتعبير جميل. لكن مجرد تعبير واحد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Did you see Lenny's face?
أرأيتم وجه "لينى"؟
You know why? Because the meaning of the music is pain.
تعرفون لما؟ لأن معنى الموسيقى مؤلم
And you're playing a painful sound.
وأنت تعزف موسيقى مؤلمة
And you look at Lenny and he's suffering.
وعندما تنظر الى "لينى" تجده يعانى
But not in a way that you want to stop.
ولكن ليس بالشكل الذى يدفعك الى التوقف
It's suffering, like, enjoying himself in a Jewish way, as they say.
انها معاناة، كانه يستمتع بالطريقة اليهودية، كما يقولون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But you can see the music on his face.
لكن يمكنكم رؤية الموسيقى على وجهه
You can see the baton left his hand. No more baton.
يمكنكم رؤية يداه بدون العصا
Now it's about you, the player,
الآن انه عنك كعازف
telling the story.
الذى يسرد القصة
Now it's a reversed thing. You're telling the story. And you're telling the story.
الآن انه أمر معكوس. انت تحكى القصة، وانت ايضاً
And even briefly, you become the storyteller
وربما بشكل بسيط تصبح القصصى بذاته
to which the community, the whole community, listens to.
حيث يستمع اليك المجتمع، المجتمع باكمله
And Bernstein enables that. Isn't that wonderful?
و "بيرنستاين" يتيح بذلك. أليس ذلك رائعاً؟
Now, if you are doing all the things we talked about, together,
والآن ان فعلت كل ما تكلمنا عنه
and maybe some others,
بالإضافة الى اشياء اخرى
you can get to this wonderful point of doing without doing.
سيمكنك من الوصول الى الغاية بلا القيام بالشىء بذاته
And for the last video, I think this is simply the best title.
وبالنسبة الى الفيديو الاخير. اظن ان هذا افضل عنوان
My friend Peter says,
صديقى "بيتر" يقول
"If you love something, give it away." So, please.
ان احببت شىء، فإعطه للآخرين" فتفضلوا "
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)